A Guide to the Records of the Commission on Local Government, 1953-2002.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Local Government, Commission on, Records
1953-2002.
The Library of Virginia
35287, 40541
Virginia. Commission on Local Government.
40 cubic feet
Biographical/Historical Information
The Commission on Local Government was created February 28, 1979, by an act of the General Assembly, and formally began operation in January, 1980. It was created at the urging of a joint Virginia Municipal League-Virginia Association of Counties task force studying annexation and boundary change laws. The Commission originally was placed under the Secretary of Commerce and Resources, and on June 7, 1983 under the Secretary of Administration and Finance. Effective July 1, 1984, the secretariats divided, and the Commission was placed under the authority of the Secretary of Administration.
The Commission's major activities include assisting in the mediation and negotiated settlement of local boundary change and governmental transition issues; reviewing proposed annexations, petitions for partial county immunity from annexation, voluntary boundary adjustments, town incorporations, town or county transitions city transitions to town status, and interlocal agreements relative to such issues, and rendering findings of fact and recommendations to the affected local governments and to the courts; assisting local governmental issues, upon request, in the investigation and analysis of other local governmental issues; developing fiscal impact statements for submission to the General Assembly on all legislation introduced which may require one or more local governments to establish a new or expand an existing public service (State and Federal mandates); undertaking comparative analysis of local fiscal conditions; providing a liaison service between the state and its localities relative to annexation issues. The Commission consists of five members who are appointed by the governor and confirmed by the General Assembly for five-year terms, with the term of one member expiring each year, subject to reappointment. Reports on annexation actions, settlement agreements, and agreements defining annexation rights are published as developed, and fiscal issues are addressed in "Comparative Revenue Capacity, Revenue Effort, and Fiscal Stress of Virginia's Counties and Cities, 1985/86 and 1986/87," prepared for the General Assembly.
he staff of the Commission provides assistance to the Local Government Advisory Council. This body, which was established by statute in 1978, serves as a forum for the discussion of state-local issues and other governmental concerns in the commonwealth. The chairman of the Council is the governor, other members are the lieutenant governor, executive directors of the Virginia Municipal League and the Virginia Association of Counties, and 22 members of local governing bodies throughout Virginia representing each of Virginia's 22 planning districts. In 1990, the Local Government Advisory Council was reorganized and was renamed the Virginia Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations. The reorganization of this body included a reduction in size, reconfigured to include six legislators, a private citizen, and a member of a regional planning district. Other changes included the method of appointment, schedule of elections, and the number of meetings required. Pursuant to Chapter 55, 2004 Virginia Acts of Assembly, the Virginia Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations was abolished effective July 1, 2004.
The Commission on Local Government was abolished as a separate agency by an act of the General Assembly in 2003, and on June 16, 2003, the Commission on Local Government was placed within the Dept. of Housing and Community Development.
Scope and Content
These records include the following series: Agency history files, 1953-2001; Director's correspondence, 1980-1997; Publications, 1981-2002; Special interest files, 1981-1997; Special project files, 1993-2002; and Studies and reports, 1972-1997 (Accession 40541); and Director's correspondence, 1981-1989 (Accession 35287).
These records include correspondence; various studies, reports and publications and their drafts and background documentation; annexation impact studies, publications, agreements and information collected from other states; meeting agendas and related documentation; legislative and budget information; public hearing transcripts and reports; mandate assessment files; photographs and publicity files.
Arranged by case file.
Acquisition Information
Accession 35287 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, March 4, 1997.
Accession 40541 was transferred by the Virginia Commission on Local Government, April 21, 2003.
Contents List
- Records - Executive Director, 1981-1989 (Accession 35287)., Extent: 7 cubic feet (7 boxes)
  - Harrisonburg / Rockinham County - Annexation Case, 1981-1989. (Box 1)
  - Kenbridge / Lunenburg County - Agreement defining annexation rights, 1981-1989. (Box 1)
  - Fredericksburg / Spotsylvania County - Annexation and immunity rights, 1981-1989. (Box 1)
  - Augusta County Partial Immunity Action, 1981-1989. (Box 1)
  - Leesburg / Loudoun County - Annexation agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 2)
  - Emporia / Greensville County - Annexation agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 2)
  - Williamsburg / James City County - Annexation agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 2)
  - Buena Vista / Rockbridge County - Annexation agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 2)
  - Waynesboro / Augusta County - Annexation action, 1981-1989. (Box 2)
  - Luray / Page County, 1981-1989. (Box 2)
  - Danville / Pittsylvania County - Annexation action and partial immunity action, 1981-1989. (Box 3)
  - Staunton / Augusta County - Intergovernmental agreements, 1981-1989. (Box 3)
  - Covington / Alleghany County - Annexation action, 1981-1989. (Box 3)
  - Waynesboro / Augusta County - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 4)
  - Bluefield / Tazewell County - Intergovernmental agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 4)
  - Strasburg / Shenandoah County - Agreement defining annexation rights, 1981-1989. (Box 4)
  - Lexington / Rockbridge County - Voluntary settlement of annexation and immunity, 1981-1989. (Box 4)
  - Bridgewater / Rockingham County - Agreement defining annexation rights, 1981-1989. (Box 4)
  - Franklin / Southampton County and Franklin / Isle of Wight County - Settlement agreements, 1981-1989. (Box 4)
  - Clintwood / Dickenson County - Agreement defining annexation rights, 1981-1989. (Box 4)
  - Staunton / Augusta County - Immunity and financial settlement proviions; Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 4)
  - Abingdon / Washington County - Annexation action, 1981-1989. (Box 4)
  - Lychburg / Campbell County - Voluntary settlement of annexation and growth sharing, 1981-1989. (Box 5)
  - Radford / Montgomery County - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 5)
  - Petersburg / Prince George County and Hopewell / Prince George County - Annexation actions, 1981-1989. (Box 5)
  - Covington / Clifton Forge / Alleghany County - Consolidation action, 1981-1989. (Box 5)
  - Emporia / Greensville County - Consolidation action, 1981-1989. (Box 5)
  - Warsaw / Richmond County - Agreement defining annexation rights, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Christiansburg / Montgomery County - Annexation, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Pulaski / Pulaski County - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Petersburg / Hopewell / Prince George County - Partial immunity actions, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Salem / Roanoke County - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Lebanon / Russell County - Annexation action, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Christiansburg / Montgomery County - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Herndon / Fairfax County - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Danville / Pittsylvania County - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Berryville / Clarke County - Agreement defining annexation rights, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Chincoteague / Accomack County - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 6)
  - Wytheville / Wythe County - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 7)
  - Manassas Park / Prince William - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 7)
  - Dayton / Rockingham County - Agreement defining annexation rights, 1981-1989. (Box 7)
  - Chatham / Pittsylvania County - Settlement agreement, 1981-1989. (Box 7)
  - Broadway / Rockingham County - Agreement defining annexation rights, 1981-1989. (Box 7)
  - Cape Charles / Northampton County - Annexation action, 1981-1989. (Box 7)
  - Clifton Forge / Alleghany County - Consolidation action, 1981-1989. (Box 7)
- Records, 1953-2002 (Accession 40541)., Extent: 33 cubic feet (33 boxes)
  - Commission on Local Government Structures and Relationships (Grayson Commission)
    - Agendas, minutes and handouts, 1986 May-1988 Dec. (Box 106)
    - Agendas, minutes and handouts, 1989 Jan-Nov. (Box 106)
    - Agendas, minutes and handouts, 1990 Jan. (Box 106)
    - Proposed legislation, 1987, 1989. (Box 106)
    - HD 69/90 - Draft and final, undated. (Box 106)
    - HB 550 - Draft and final, 1990. (Box 106)
    - Correspondence and documents from members, 1987-1990. (Box 106)
    - Statement to the Commission on Local Government, 1987. (Box 106)
    - Staff research for the Commission on Local Government, undated. (Box 106)
    - Addendum Budget Proposal for Commission on Local Government, 1989. (Box 106)
    - Correspondence concerning the Commission for Local Government, 1987-1990. (Box 106)
    - Virginia Municipal League - Virginia Association of Counties Task Force on Intergovernmental Relations, 1987-1991. (Box 106)
    - Coalition for Effective Local Government, 1990. (Box 106)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and other documents, undated. (Box 106)
    - Virginia Economic Outlook and City-County Structure, undated. (Box 106)
  - Studies and Reports
    - Town-County Fiscal Relations - HJR 137, 1992. (Box 107)
    - Annexation Impact Study, 1988-1990. (Box 107)
    - Annexation Impact Study - Item 76, Budget and Report, 1988-1990. (Box 107)
    - Annexation Impact Study - Staff Research, 1988-1990. (Box 107)
    - Annexation Impact Study - Audio tapes of Public Hearings, 1988-1990. (Box 107)
    - Annexation Impact Study - Public Hearing Transcripts and staff research, 1988-1990. (Box 107)
    - Annexation Impact Study - Danville/Pittsylvania fiscal documents, 1988-1990. (Box 107)
    - Annexation Impact Study - Staff research, 1988-1990. (Box 108)
    - Development of State Mediation Resources, 1989. (Box 108)
    - Local Government Issues Related to Neglected or Abandoned Cemeteries (SJR 319), 1997. (Box 108)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Interim Report, 1974. (Box 109)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Final Report (original and first revision), 1974 Oct. (Box 109)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Final Report (second and final revision), 1975 Jan. (Box 109)
    - Commission for City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Sites for Solid Waste Disposal - HD 33, 1976. (Box 109)
    - Commission on State Aid to Localities and the Joint Subcommittee on Annexation, 1977. (Box 109)
    - Commission on State Aid to Localities and the Joint Subcommittee on Annexation - Law Enforcement Formula Development, 1977-1978. (Box 109)
    - Commission on State Aid to Localities and the Joint Subcommittee on Annexation - Virginia Municipal League and Virginia Association of Counties Task Force on Annexation, 1977-1978. (Box 109)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - HB 602, 1978-1979. (Box 109)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - HB 603, 1978-1979. (Box 109)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - HB 855, 1976. (Box 110)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Staff research, 1972-1974. (Box 110)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Administrative and correspondence files, 1974-1975. (Box 110)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Presentations, 1972-1974. (Box 110)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Working papers, 1972-1974. (Box 110)
    - Commission on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Minutes, 1972-1974. (Box 110)
    - Joint Subcommittee Studying Government in Urban Cities (HJR 171), 1978. (Box 111)
    - Joint Subcomittee Studying Local Fiscal Needs (HB 2160), 1976. (Box 111)
    - Joint Subcommittee Studying Local Fiscal Needs - Article: State Aid to Localities (HB 2160), 1977. (Box 111)
    - Committee on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Subcommittee on the Minnesota Plan, 1976. (Box 111)
    - Committee on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Legislative Review #1, 1976. (Box 111)
    - Committee on City-County Relationships (CCCR) - Legislative Review #2, 1976. (Box 111)
    - Committee on City County Relationships (CCCR) - Legislative Review, 1975. (Box 111)
    - Project Streamline - Grant procedures, 1991-1995. (Box 112)
    - Establishment of the State Intergovernmental Relations Commission (SJR 119), 1988. (Box 112)
  - Agency History files
    - Local Government Advisory Council, 1977-1991. (Box 112)
    - Local Government Advisory Council - Minutes, 1977-1991. (Box 112)
  - Publications
    - Report: Harrisonburg - Rockingham County, Annexation, 1981 Feb. (Box 113)
    - Report: Kenbridge - Lunenburg County, Agreement, 1981 Oct. (Box 113)
    - Report: Fredericksburg - Spotsylvania County, Annexation and Immunity, 1982 June. (Box 113)
    - Report: Augusta County, Partial Immunity, 1982 Dec. (Box 113)
    - Report: Leesburg - Loudoun County, Agreement, 1983 Mar. (Box 113)
    - Report: Emporia - Greensville County, Agreement, 1983 May. (Box 113)
    - Report: Williamsburg - James City County, Agreement, 1983 June. (Box 113)
    - Report: Buena Vista - Rockbridge County, Agreement, 1983 June. (Box 113)
    - Report: Waynesboro - Augusta County, Annexation, 1983 July. (Box 113)
    - Report: Waynesboro - Augusta County, Financial Settlement, 1983 Aug. (Box 113)
    - Report: Luray - Page County, Annexation, 1983 Aug. (Box 113)
    - Report: Danville Annexation - Pittsylvania County, Immunity, 1984 Feb. (Box 113)
    - Report: Staunton - Augusta County, Agreement, 1984 June. (Box 113)
    - Report: Covington - Alleghany County, Annexation, 1984 Aug. (Box 113)
    - Report: Waynesboro - Augusta County, Agreement, 1984 Oct. (Box 113)
    - Report: Bluefield - Tazewell County, Agreement, 1984 Oct. (Box 113)
    - Report: Strasburg - Shenandoah County, Agreement, 1984 Dec. (Box 113)
    - Report: Lexington - Rockbridge County, Agreement, 1985 Feb. (Box 114)
    - Report: Bridgewater - Rockingham County, Agreement, 1985 Mar. (Box 114)
    - Report: Franklin - Southampton County and Isle of Wight County, Agreements, 1985 July. (Box 114)
    - Report: Clintwood - Dickenson County, Agreement, 1985 Aug. (Box 114)
    - Report: Staunton - Augusta County, Financial and Immunity Settlement Agreement, 1985 Sept. (Box 114)
    - Report: Abingdon - Washington County, Agreement, 1985 Nov. (Box 114)
    - Report: Lynchburg - Campbell County, Agreement, 19. (Box 114)
    - Report: Franklin - Isle of Wight, Revised Agreement, 1986 May. (Box 114)
    - Report: Radford - Montgomery County, Agreement, 1986 June. (Box 114)
    - Report: Petersburg - Hopewell - Prince George County, Annexation, 1986 June. (Box 114)
    - Report: Covington - Clifton Forge - Alleghany County, Consolidation, 1986 July. (Box 114)
    - Report: Emporia - Greensville County, Consolidation, 1986 July. (Box 114)
    - Report: Warsaw - Richmond County, Agreement, 1986 Nov. (Box 114)
    - Report: Christiansburg - Montgomery County, Annexation, 1987 Feb. (Box 114)
    - Report: Pulaski - Pulaski County, Agreement 1987 Mar. (Box 114)
    - Report: Petersburg - Hopewell - Prince George County, Immunity, 1987 Apr. (Box 114)
    - Report: Salem - Roanoke County, Agreement, 1987 June. (Box 115)
    - Report: Lebanon - Russell County, Agreement, 1987 June. (Box 115)
    - Report: Christiansburg - Montgomery County, Agreement, 1987 Oct. (Box 115)
    - Report: Herndon - Fairfax County, Agreement, 1987 Oct. (Box 115)
    - Report: Danville - Pittsylvania County, Agreement, 1987 Dec. (Box 115)
    - Report: Berryville - Clarke County, Agreement, 1988 Nov. (Box 115)
    - Impact of Annexation - State Mandates and Regulations, 1988 Dec. (Box 115)
    - Report: Chincoteague - Accomack County, Agreement, 1989 Jan. (Box 115)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1985/1986 and 1986/1987, 1989 June. (Box 115)
    - Directory of State Assistance to Local Governments, 1989 June. (Box 115)
    - Report: Wytheville - Wythe County, Agreement, 1989 Sept. (Box 115)
    - Report: Manassas Park - Prince William County, Agreement, 1989 Oct. (Box 115)
    - Alternative Dispute Resolution, 1990 Jan. (Box 115)
    - Report: Dayton - Rockingham County, Agreement, 1990 Jan. (Box 115)
    - Higher Education Resources, 1990 Jan. (Box 115)
    - Report: Chatham - Pittsylvania County, Agreement, 1990 Jan. (Box 115)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1987/1988, 1990 Aug. (Box 115)
    - Directory of Local Government Assistance, 1990 Sept. (Box 115)
    - Report: Broadway - Rockingham County, Agreement, 1990 Oct. (Box 115)
    - Report: Cape Charles - Northampton County, Annexation, 1991 Feb. (Box 116)
    - Report: Clifton Forge - Alleghany County, Consolidation, 1991 Aug. (Box 116)
    - Report: Carriage Hill, et al., Bedford - Bedford County, Annexation, 1991 Sept. (Box 116)
    - Report: Orange - Orange County, Agreement, 1991 Sept. (Box 116)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1988/1989, 1991 Sept. (Box 116)
    - Report: South Boston - Halifax County, Reversion, 1992 Jan. (Box 116)
    - Privatization of Local Government Services in Virginia, 1992 Mar. (Box 116)
    - Report: Farmville - Prince Edward County, Agreement, 1992 May. (Box 116)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1989/1990, 1992 June. (Box 116)
    - Directory of Local Government Assistance, 1992 Aug. (Box 116)
    - Report: Radford - Montgomery County, Revenue Sharing Agreement, 1992 Dec. (Box 116)
    - Change in the Commonwealth - City/County Experience in the 1990s, 1993 Mar. (Box 116)
    - Report: Bedford - Bedford County, Agreement, 1993 Apr. (Box 116)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1990/1991, 1993 June. (Box 116)
    - Report: Amherst - Amherst County, Agreement, 1993 Aug. (Box 116)
    - Report: Colonial Beach - Westmoreland County, Agreement, 1993 Oct. (Box 116)
    - Report: Purcellville - Loudoun County, Agreement, 1994 Jan. (Box 116)
    - Report: Colonial Beach - Westmoreland County, School Funding Arbitration, 1994 Feb. (Box 116)
    - Change in the Commonwealth - Town Experience in the 1990s, 1994 May. (Box 116)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1991/1992, 1994 July. (Box 116)
    - Directory of Local Government Assistance, 1994 Oct. (Box 116)
    - Catalog of Mandates, 1995 Mar. (Box 117)
    - Hillsville - Carroll County, Agreement, 1995 Mar. (Box 117)
    - Report: Bedford - Bedford County, Consolidation, 1995 June. (Box 117)
    - Conparative Fiscal Stress 1992/1993, 1995 July. (Box 117)
    - Report: Ashland - Hanover County, Agreement, 1995 July. (Box 117)
    - Report: Pearisburg - Giles County, Agreement, 1995 Dec. (Box 117)
    - Report: Winchester - Frederick County, Agreement, 1996 Jan. (Box 117)
    - Report: Round Hill - Loudoun County, Agreement, 1996 May. (Box 117)
    - Report: Manassas - Prince William County, Agreement, 1996 July. (Box 117)
    - Local-Source Revenue Profile 1994 and 1989/1994, 1996 June. (Box 117)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1993/1994, 1996 Aug. (Box 117)
    - Catalog of Mandates, 1996 Sept. (Box 117)
    - Report: Bowling Green - Caroline County, Agreement, 1996 Sept. (Box 117)
    - Report: Bridgewater - Rockingham County, Agreement, 1997 Jan. (Box 117)
    - Report: Bristol - Washington County, Sharing Agreement, 1997 Mar. (Box 117)
    - Report: Smithfield - Isle of Wight County, Agreement, 1997 May. (Box 117)
    - Local-Source Revenue Profile 1989-1995, 1997 June. (Box 118)
    - Personal Property Tax Revenue 1989-1996, 1997 Aug. (Box 118)
    - Report: Pearisburg - Giles County, Agreement, 1997 July. (Box 118)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1994/1995, 1997 Aug. (Box 118)
    - Catalog of Mandates, 1997 Sept. (Box 118)
    - Report: Bedford - Bedford County, Revenue Sharing Agreement, 1997 Nov. (Box 118)
    - Neglected or Abandoned For-Profit Cemeteries, 1998 Jan. (Box 118)
    - Impact of Aesthetics on Economy and Quality of Life in Virginia, 1998 Apr. (Box 118)
    - Report: Boyce - Clarke County, Agreement, 1998 May. (Box 118)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1995/1996, 1998 July. (Box 118)
    - Profiles of Regional Government Structures in North America, 1998 Aug. (Box 118)
    - Operating Expenditure Profile of Cities and Counties, 1990-1997, 1998 Aug. (Box 118)
    - Catalog of Mandates, 1998 Sept. (Box 118)
    - Advisor Commission on Intergovernmental Relations (ACIR) Biennial Report, 1998 Oct. (Box 119)
    - Report: Franklin - Southampton County, Revenue Sharing Agreement, 1999 Feb. (Box 118)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1996/1997, 1999 May. (Box 119)
    - Report: Front Royal - Warren County, Agreement, 1999 June. (Box 119)
    - Catalog of Mandates, 1999 Sept. (Box 119)
    - Report: Vinton - Roanoke County, Revenue Sharing Agreement, 1999 Oct. (Box 119)
    - Report: Prices Fork Incorporation as Town in Montgomery County, 1999 Nov. (Box 119)
    - Report: Rocky Mounty - Franklin County, Agreement, 1999 Nov. (Box 119)
    - Report: Rocky Mounty - Franklin County, Agreement, 1999 Nov. (Box 119)
    - Impact of Aesthetics on Economy and Quality of Life in Virginia, 2000 Mar. (Box 119)
    - Comparative Fiscal Stress 1997/1998, 2000 May. (Box 119)